Else von Richthofen Collection MS008
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Letters and correspondence, 1898 -- 1947; 1900 -- 1915; MS008.001; 0.75 Linear Feet; 190 Digital Object(s) Each transcript has two versions - one in PDF and the other in MS Word.; 9.5 Megabytes
  - Sofie [Riehl] her aunt to Freidl [Freida Gross], 1908; MS008.001.003.00126; Riehl, Sofie (Box 3)
    She is relating her grief about Helene's death and begs Freida not to disclose anything about Helene as a person. She talks about moving to Berlin and vacationing at a resort on the Kaltic Sea. She mentions Lasso (family member?) and the Brooks (family friends). Tells her how much she needs her. [black edging on stationary]
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Von Richthofen], 1908; MS008.001.003.00200; Gross, Frieda (Box 3)
    In spirit Freida is sharing her thoughts with Else and she wishes they could be together. She talks about the baptism of Arnold, Friedrich, Ernst. Calls Munich a blessed city and feels Graz is dreadful. [This is a continuation of the correspondence Frieda Gross to Else Von Richthofen. It joins up with #99]
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.003.00201; Gross, Frieda (Box 3)
    Fragment. Frieda states that the music of "Tristan" [by Wagner] and Beethoven are one of life's best experiences. They are some of the few things making life worthwhile. She sees herself as remaining the same, never getting old and perhaps never mature.
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Von Richthofen]., MS008.001.003.00202; Gross, Frieda (Box 3)
    Fragment. She talks about friends, wants to keep her relationships with Rupprecht as a father-daughter type. She mentions Hickson who will publish in a philosophical journal. She talks about the concern for her father's well-being. Her daily routine is practicing piano, studying philosophy and caring for the poor.
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else Von Richthofen]., MS008.001.003.00203; Gross, Frieda (Box 3)
    Fragment. Frieda is referring to someone whom she is very fond of and has a terminal illness. He will return to America [Smith ?] and probably will forget her quickly if he should get better.
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else Von Richthofen], MS008.001.003.00204; Gross, Frieda (Box 3)
    Fragment. Frieda is very happy, but only Else is supposed to know about the reasons for it. She states her life is "immersed in gold" [could imply her enormous happiness]. She expresses her joy and wants to know more.
  - Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.003.00205; Von Richthofen, Else (Box 3)
    [Copy of an autobiographical statement by Else Von Richthofen] An autobigraphical summary of important periods and events in Else Von Richthofen's life and the people who are connected with them. Changing relationship with husband Edgar Jaffe from the feeling of protection to disappointment. Relationship with Volcker, her physician. Relationship with Otto Gross--his teachings of erotic freedom and the effect it had. Met Max and Marianne Weber through childhood friend Frieda Gross. Enduring relationship with Alfred Weber, brother of Max Weber, whom she viewed as possessive and coercive at times.
  - Transcriptions on CD, 1900 -- 1947; MS008.001.003.00206 (Box 3)
  - Unsorted letters in German script, MS008.001.003.00207; Von Richthofen, Else (Box 3)
  - Marianne Weber to Else von Richthofen in German script, MS008.001.003.00208; Von Richthofen, Else (Box 3)
    Eleven letters from Marianne Weber to Else von Richthofen in German script.
  - Transcripts of letters # 45-95, MS008.001.003.00209; Von Richthofen, Else (Box 3)
  - Digital transcripts of letters, 1900-1947; MS008.001.00001; 190 Digital Object(s) Each transcript has two versions - one in Word and the other in PDF.; 9.5 Megabytes
    Transcription of von Richthofen correspondence provided by Frieda Schlofer, November 2007, on electronic media.
    - 1 12.6.1900 an Else, 1900-06-12; MS008.001.00001.00001
      Letter transcript.
    - 2 26.6.1900 Fortsetzung 202 an Else, 1900-06-26; MS008.001.00001.00002
    - 3 26.7.1900 an Else, 1900-07-26; MS008.001.00001.00003
    - 4 18.8.1900 an Else, 1900-08-18; MS008.001.00001.00004
    - 5 3.12.1900 an Else, 1900-12-03; MS008.001.00001.00005
    - 7 22.12.(1900) an Else, 1900-12-22; MS008.001.00001.00006
    - 9 5.1.1901 Fortsetzung 96 an Else, 1901-01-05; MS008.001.00001.00007
    - 10 12.2.1901 an Else, 1901-02-12; MS008.001.00001.00008
    - 12 18.3.1901 an Else, 1901-03-18; MS008.001.00001.00009
    - 13 15.4.1901 Fortsetzung 201 an Else, 1901-04-15; MS008.001.00001.00011
    - 14 26.5.1901 an Else, 1901-05-26; MS008.001.00001.00012
    - 15 12.6.1901 an Else, 1901-06-12; MS008.001.00001.00013
    - 16 18.7.1901 an Else, 1901-07-18; MS008.001.00001.00014
    - 17 15.8.1901 Fortsetzung 98 an Else, 1901-08-15; MS008.001.00001.00015
    - 18 26.8.1901 an Else, 1901-08-26; MS008.001.00001.00016
    - 19 17.11.1901 an Else, 1901-11-17; MS008.001.00001.00017
    - 20 22.11.1901 an Else, 1901-11-22; MS008.001.00001.00018
    - 21 30.12.1901 Forts. 203 an Else, 1901-12-30; MS008.001.00001.00024
    - 22 9.1.1902 an Else, 1902-01-09; MS008.001.00001.00025
    - 24 16.5.1902 an Else, 1902-05-16; MS008.001.00001.00026
    - 25 (21.3.1902) Anfang 99 an Else, 1902-03-21; MS008.001.00001.00027
    - 26 13.6.1902 an Else, 1902-06-13; MS008.001.00001.00028
    - 27 20.6.1902 Fortsetzung 204 an Else, 1902-06-20; MS008.001.00001.00029
    - 28 1.10.1902 an Else, 1902-10-01; MS008.001.00001.00030
    - 29 5.10.1902 an Else, 1902-10-05; MS008.001.00001.00031
    - 30 14.2.1903 an Else, 1903-02-14; MS008.001.00001.00032
    - 31 6.5.1903 an Else, 1903-05-06; MS008.001.00001.00033
    - 32 24.7.1904 an Else, 1904-07-24; MS008.001.00001.00034
    - 34 2.9.1906 an Else, 1906-09-02; MS008.001.00001.00035
    - 35 20.2.1906 an Else, 1906-02-20; MS008.001.00001.00036
    - 36 17.4.(1907) an Else, 1907-04-17; MS008.001.00001.00037
    - 37 23.3.(1907) an Else, 1907-03-23; MS008.001.00001.00038
    - 39 28.4.(1907) Fragment an Else, 1907-04-28; MS008.001.00001.00039
    - 40 17.8.(1907) an Else, 1907-08-17; MS008.001.00001.00040
    - 41 22.8.(1907) an Else, 1907-08-22; MS008.001.00001.00041
    - 42 25.8.(1909) an Else.doc., 1909-08-25; MS008.001.00001.00042
    - 43 4.10.(1909) Fragment an Else, 1909-10-04; MS008.001.00001.00043
    - 44 20.2.(1901) an Else, 1901-02-20; MS008.001.00001.00044
    - 45 2.9.(1911) Anf.51 Forts.62an Else, 1911-09-02; MS008.001.00001.00045
    - 46 (16.)2.(1911) an Else, 1911-02-16; MS008.001.00001.00046
    - 47 12.3.1911 an Else, 1911-03-12; MS008.001.00001.00047
    - 48 10.4.(1911) an Else, 1911-04-10; MS008.001.00001.00048
    - 49 6.8.(1911) an Else, 1911-08-06; MS008.001.00001.00049
    - 50 11.8.(1911) Fragment an Else, 1911-08-11; MS008.001.00001.00050
    - 51 2.9.(1911) Forts. 4562 an Else, 1911-09-02; MS008.001.00001.00051
    - 52 9.10.(1911) an Else, 1911-10-09; MS008.001.00001.00052
    - 55 (7.10.1912) an Else, 1912-10-07; MS008.001.00001.00053
    - 56 6.5.(1912) Fragment an Else, 1912-05-06; MS008.001.00001.00054
    - 58 14.6.(1912) Fragment an Else, 1912-06-14; MS008.001.00001.00055
    - 59 22.6.(1912) an Else, 1912-06-22; MS008.001.00001.00056
    - 60 (26.)7.(1912) an Else, 1912-07-26; MS008.001.00001.00057
    - 61 1.10.(1913) an Else, 1913-10-01; MS008.001.00001.00058
    - 62 2.9.1911 Anfang 51 u. 45 an Else, 1911-09-02; MS008.001.00001.00059
    - 63 15.9.(1912) an Else, 1912-09-15; MS008.001.00001.00060
    - 64 o.Dat.(1920+) Fragment an Else, MS008.001.00001.00061
    - 65 6.6.(1913) Fragment an Else, 1913-06-06; MS008.001.00001.00062
    - 67 6.7.(1914) an Else, 1914-07-06; MS008.001.00001.00063
    - 68 ( Okt.1915) an Else, 1915-10-01; MS008.001.00001.00064
    - 69a 2.11.(1915) an Else, 1915-11-02; MS008.001.00001.00065
    - 69b Nachtrag zu 69a an Else, 1915-11-02; MS008.001.00001.00066
    - 70 o.Dat. (n. Weihn. 1915) an Else, 1915-12-25; MS008.001.00001.00067
    - 71 o.Dat. (1916-17) an Else, 1916 -- 1917; MS008.001.00001.00068
    - 72 21.10.(1916-17) an Else, 1916 -- 1917; MS008.001.00001.00069
    - 73 30.12.(1917) an Else, 1917-12-30; MS008.001.00001.00070
    - 74 17.9.1919 an Else, 1919-09-17; MS008.001.00001.00071
    - 75 (1920) Fragment an Else, MS008.001.00001.00072
    - 76 22.12.(1919) an Else, 1905-04-02; MS008.001.00001.00073
    - 77 12.10.(~1930) an Else, 1930-10-12; MS008.001.00001.00074
    - 78 o.Dat.(1921-22) an Else, 1921 -- 1922; MS008.001.00001.00075
    - 79 25.1.(~1920)an Else, 1920-01-25; MS008.001.00001.00076
    - 80 27.5.1922 an Else, 1922-05-27; MS008.001.00001.00077
    - 81 18.6.1922 an Else, 1922-06-18; MS008.001.00001.00078
    - 82 22.6.1922 an Else, 1922-06-22; MS008.001.00001.00079
    - 84 29.9.(1922) an Else, 1922-09-29; MS008.001.00001.00080
    - 85 24.10.1922 an Else, 1922-10-24; MS008.001.00001.00081
    - 86 8.1.1923 an Else, 1923-01-08; MS008.001.00001.00082
    - 87 31.1.1930 an Else, 1930-01-31; MS008.001.00001.00083
    - 88 1.11.1930 an Else, 1930-11-01; MS008.001.00001.00084
    - 89 31.7.1940 an Else, 1940-07-31; MS008.001.00001.00085
    - 90 27.9.1941 an Else, 1941-09-27; MS008.001.00001.00086
    - 91 12.(1942-43) an Else, 1942 -- 1943; MS008.001.00001.00087
    - 93 30.10.(1946) an Else, 1946-10-30; MS008.001.00001.00088
    - 94 17.5.1947 an Else, 1947-05-17; MS008.001.00001.00089
    - 95 5.10.(1940) an Else, 1940-10-05; MS008.001.00001.00090
    - 96 (5.1.1901) Anfang 9 an Else, 1901-01-05; MS008.001.00001.00091
    - 97 o.Dat.(1900) an Else, MS008.001.00001.00092
    - 98 16.(8.1901) Anfang 17 an Else, 1901-08-16; MS008.001.00001.00093
    - 99 21.3.(1902) Fortsetzung 25 an Else, 1902-03-21; MS008.001.00001.00094
    - 123 22.12.(1914) an Else, 1914-12-22; MS008.001.00001.00010
    - 200 7.10.(1901). an Else, 1901-10-07; MS008.001.00001.00019
    - 201 (15.4.1901) Anfang 13 an Else, 1901-04-15; MS008.001.00001.00020
    - 202 (26.6.1900) Anfang 2 an Else, 1900-06-26; MS008.001.00001.00021
    - 203 (30.12.1901) Anfang 21 an Else, 1901-12-30; MS008.001.00001.00022
    - 204 (20.6.1902) Anfang 27 an Else, 1902-06-20; MS008.001.00001.00023
    - Anmerkungen, MS008.001.00001.00095
- Research material, 1915 -- 1984; 1960 -- 1985; MS008.002; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Material collected by Tufts University professor Martin Green for research in writing the two books "The Mountain of Truth" and "The von Richthofen Sisters." The research material contains copies of letters, articles and photographs related to the Ascona (Switzerland) movement. Ascona was the center for "New Age" activities in the early part of the twentieth century. There are also letters from Hermann Muller, a German scholar, concerning Muller's work on Gusto Groser, the "nature man," and his influence on Hesse, the German novelist. There are also copies of letters from the influential German dance instructor Rudolf von Laban to Brandenberg. In addition, there are copies of essays by the criminologist Hanns Gross (father of Otto Gross), Alfred Weber, Nohl, and letters related to variious Ascona personalities, including Lisa Ullmann and the Perrottet family. Finally, there are copies of articles by and about Otto Gross and a program from the Ascona Festival of 1978.
  This series is arranged as found.
  - The Ascona File, MS008.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, The Muller letter, 1984; MS008.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, The Muller letter, 1984; MS008.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, The Muller letter, 1984; MS008.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, The Muller letter, 1984; MS008.002.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, The Muller letters and essays on Hensseby Graser and Blatter about Lusto Graser [student in Munich studied Gusto Grosser (in German)], MS008.002.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Theater Pamphlets and Pictures, MS008.002.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Otto Gross's Work and Articles about Otto Gross, MS008.002.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Otto Gross: Published Essays, MS008.002.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Program etc. of 1978 Ascona Festival, photograph/ photocopy (in German), MS008.002.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Rudolf Laban to Hans Brandenburg (in German). The Ascona File: copies from the Stad.bib Munich, 1919 -- 1923; MS008.002.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Muller Letter, 1957; MS008.002.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Replies to various letters of Inquiry to various archives/ Freida's Essay on Schiller/ Else's Interview with Lois Hoffman, MS008.002.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Letters from (not by) Muller, 1915 -- 1919; MS008.002.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Ida Oedankover: 2 essays/reviews of Zunada Omeuda (a props (tracer)), Postcards from Szeeman/ Essay by Nohl, Essay by Alfred Weber, MS008.002.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - The Ascona File, Letters Relative to Laban: from Lisa Ullmann and the Perottet Family, Letters from September to December, 1983 -- 1984; MS008.002.004.00016 (Box 4)